Javaram Hariharan

Email: jayaramhariharan@utexas.edu Website: jayaramhariharan.com Mobile: +1-203-249-4265GitHub: github.com/elbeejay Twitter: @HariharanJay

Research Interests

My research leverages numerical models and remote sensing data to answer questions at the intersection of civil engineering and geology. In particular I am interested in understanding how fluvial-deltaic environments will evolve under changing external conditions.

EDUCATION

• The University of Texas at Austin

Austin. TX

PhD, Civil Engineering

May 2019 - May 2022 (Expected)

• Thesis: Top to Bottom: Modeling and Analyzing River Delta Surface Morphology and Subsurface Form

MS, Civil Engineering

Aug. 2017 - May 2019

• Thesis: Quantifying the Influence of Surface Processes on Subsurface Geometry in Deltaic Environments

• University of Maryland, College Park

BS, Civil and Environmental Engineering

College Park, MD Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2014

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug. 2017 - Present

- Numerical modeling of river delta evolution and growth
- Graph theoretical analysis of river delta morphology
- Surface-Subsurface relationship in river deltas

• Los Alamos National Laboratory

Student Intern

Los Alamos, NM Jan. 2021 - Jun. 2021

- Applying graph theory to better quantify flux partitioning in river deltas
- Gutschick, Little & Weber P.A.

Civil Engineer

Burtonsville, MD Jan. 2015 - Jul. 2017

- Led civil engineering site design for 2 commercial land development projects
- Provided expert testimony at Planning Board meetings and public hearings

Publications

- [6] Hariharan, J., A. Moodie, and P. Passalacqua (submitted). Spectral Band Synthesis: Using Previously Trained Models on New Data, Earth and Space Science.
- [5] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, E. Steel, C. Paola, H.A. Michael (under review), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 2: Relating Subsurface Geometry to Groundwater Flow Behavior, Water Resources Research.
- [4] Hariharan, J., Z. Xu, H.A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel, P. Passalacqua (under review), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 1: Relating Surface and Subsurface Geometries, Water Resources Research.
- [3] Miltenberger, A.M, T. Mukerji, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, E. Nesvold (under review), A Graph-Theoretic Monte Carlo Framework for Comparing Delta Morphology, Morphodynamics, and Stratigraphy in Numerical Models and Physical Experiments, Mathematical Geosciences.

- [2] Schwenk, J., J. Hariharan (2021), RivGraph: Automatic Extraction and Analysis of River and Delta Channel Network Topology, Journal of Open Source Software, 6(59), 2952, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.02952.
- [1] **Hariharan, J.**, K. Wright, and P. Passalacqua (2020), dorado: A Python package for simulating passive particle transport in shallow-water flows, Journal of Open Source Software, 5(54), 2585, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.02585.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Graduate Teaching Assistant

• Substitute lecturer for the hydrology and stochastic hydrology courses

Fall 2019

• Teaching assistant for undergraduate hydraulic engineering course

Spring 2020

• Grader for undergraduate hydraulics and hydrology courses

Fall 2018, 2019, and 2020

Conference Abstracts and Presentations

- [10] **Hariharan, J.**, K. Wright, P. Passalacqua (2021), Modeling The Influence Of Polders On River Delta Connectivity, 8th International Conference on Water and Flood Management, Abstract 100261.
- [9] Tull, N., S. Rahman, P. Passalacqua, K. Wright, J. Hariharan, H. Hassenruck-Gudipati, D. Mohrig (2020),
 Determining Local Mesh Resolution for Accurate Modeling of River-Floodplain Connectivity, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract H137-003
- [8] Moodie, A. J., **J. Hariharan**, J. Caers, P. Passalacqua (2020), Constraining autogenic smaller-scale stratigraphic variability via information theoretic relationships with larger-scale observations, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP025-06
- [7] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, H. A. Michael (2019), Contaminant transport in deltaic aquifers: The impact of surface-to-subsurface connectivity, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2237
- [6] Steel, E., C. Paola, P. Passalacqua, H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, Z. Xu (2019), Linking surface dynamics to the subsurface record: the effectiveness of overhead imagery in quantifying depositional architecture, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2236
- [5] **Hariharan**, J., P. Passalacqua (2019), Modeling Deltaic Evolution Amidst Anthropomorphic Development, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP23E-2261
- [4] Miltenberger, A., T. Mukerji, P. Passalacqua, J. Hariharan (2019), Comparing a Delta Numerical Model to a Flume Experiment using Monte Carlo Simulations and Graph Theory, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP31A-06
- [3] Michael, H. A., Z. Xu, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, M. C. Perignon (2018), Surface to Subsurface Connectivity in River Deltas: From Depositional Processes to Preferential Groundwater Flow, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP42A-07.
- [2] Xu, Z., H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, M. C. Perignon, E. Steel (2018), Relations between static and dynamic connectivity in a deltaic aquifer, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2744.
- [1] **Hariharan, J.**, M.C. Perignon, P. Passalacqua, Z. Xu, H. A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel (2018), Quantifying Connectivity Between the Surface and Subsurface in Numerically Modeled Deltas, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2746.

ACADEMIC AND VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

• Academic Activities

• UT Austin: Graduate and Industry Networking (GAIN) committee member

2018

• UT Austin: Environmental and Water Resources Engineering Seminar committee member

2018

• CSDMS: Interactive Teaching Material Creation

Dec. 2020

- * Creator of EKT Lab: Alternative mesh generation for Landlab [link]
- Peer-reviewer: Computers & Geosciences; Journal of Open Source Software

• Volunteer Activities

• St. David's Hospital, Austin, TX: Weekly Volunteer (3 hrs/wk)

Apr. 2019 - Apr. 2020

Grants and Awards

• Grants

 $\circ\,$ NSF Supplement: INTERN Funding Opportunity (\$44,999)

FY 2020

Awards

• University Graduate Continuing Fellowship

2021-2022

 $\circ~$ Trigg and Fannie E. Twichell Centennial Endowed Presidential Scholarship

2020

Earnest and Agnes Gloyna Endowed Presidential Scholarship

2019

 $\circ~$ Walter L. and Reta Mae Moore Graduate Fellowship in Water Resources

2017

• University of Maryland President's Scholarship

2011 - 2014

SHORT COURSES

• Short Courses

 \circ Earth Surface Processes Modeling Summer Institute [CSDMS]

2020

• Summer Institute for Earth-Surface Dynamics [NCED]

2018

SKILLS AND LICENSES

• Skills

- o Programming/Scripting: Python, LATEX, MATLAB, Julia, Kotlin, Git, Unix, Bash, Unit Testing
- Engineering/Mapping: AutoCAD Civil 3D, HEC-RAS, ArcGIS/QGIS, AutoTURN
- o Other: MS Office, GIMP, Inkscape, IHS Kingdom, Audacity

• Licenses

• State of Maryland Engineer in Training (EIT)

Licence #46507

Non-refereed Publications

- [2] Hariharan, J. (2020), py_gee_tools v0.1, Zenodo, http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4331356
- [1] **Hariharan**, J. (2019), Quantifying the Influence of Surface Processes on Subsurface Geometry in Deltaic Environments, M.S. Thesis, University of Texas, Austin